Welcome to another episode of Kizar Talk
Show.
If you are watching this offline,
play at 1.5 speed or higher.
Uh
I don't have anything much planned
except just this one. So, we going to
show you so this will be like Emacs
workflow. So, you just going to watch me
uh
create a new webpage for my Emac list
one of the Emac list fantastic Emac list
command I wrote on a spot yesterday.
So, if you are here, say hi.
Uh I don't have much
uh to do. So, um
>> [clears throat]
>> So, today maybe just 10 minutes, 15
minutes, maybe.
Okay, so
Okay, so yeah, so here is my Emacs. Here
is my Windows showing all the command
calls and keystrokes. That's a pink
window.
Okay, there is this my Emacs. So, let me
begin. So, yesterday we I be I wrote
this command fantastic. What is it for?
For example, if you go to CSS cascading
style sheet.
Uh and for example, you got this media
query with equals to greater than 54
root em. Em is a root font size.
So, sometimes you want to convert it to
pixels. So, you see, let me demonstrate,
okay?
Press the key. You see, now it became
864 pixels.
Uh press the key again, it became 54
rem. So, it automatically convert. And
you can see the command is Kizar CSS
toggle pixel to rem. Fantastic. Let me
do it again. So, let's go to um
somewhere. Let's see, did I make any
change? No. So, let's say I didn't you
know, let's just say I copy this. Okay,
copy that, make a copy here, and let's
say
let's say 1,000 pixel. Okay, which is
common for
uh let's make it one line. Okay,
for um
media query. Okay, so I want to convert
this to
root font size REM. So, press the key,
you see 62.5
REM. Fantastic and beautiful. Press the
key again, it's back. See?
Delete that. Okay, close. So, that's a
demo of this command. Uh okay, so
where's the command source code? So,
describe key press press, that's the
key, and the command is x CSS toggle
pixel REM. And in this file, x CSS mode.
Uh now, this mode is not public. It was
you know, a long time ago, but
uh
but I removed all my GitHub because
nobody give a damn.
Uh so, these days, if you really want,
you can donate me. Like, donate me $100.
Like,
I'm you know, so you if you go to my uh
Emacs website, if you are here, say hi.
Okay? If you go to my Emacs website,
xahlee.info,
you can see um
So, xah fly keys, xah Emacs packages.
So, you got my Emacs Lisp packages, my
math input mode, my find replace
package, you know, all of my packages.
And one of them is CSS. So, you can see
this is my own CSS code.
Which you don't need because the the
built-in bundle default CSS mode is
pretty good. Okay? Of course, my mode
got my own several uh new but yeah, you
don't need it.
>> [snorts]
>> So, anyway, so I but I was saying, you
know, I got all these
uh packages
and uh it used to be free for like 10
years, but nobody give a damn, so I
removed it.
So, right now it's just soft like keys.
It's the most important and most
powerful, most useful that's on GitHub.
You know, you can grab and I have
I have like 50 videos demonstrating soft
like keys, which I which is what I'm
using right now.
Okay, soft like keys, uh check it out.
Okay, so now, so anyway, so I want to
show you this command then. This I coded
on the fly yesterday. Why do I code it?
Because
because it turns out uh if you go to
cascading style sheet, if you are web
dev, then you know.
Uh
you know, so uh if you do media very. In
fact, it is better if you use REM, root
font size instead of the pixels
because
because often times people increase the
font size on their phone
or on in the browser or via the system.
For example, uh if you on Windows, you
have the operating system.
So, you go to here display and you go
here scale and there is text size, you
see?
So, I have it enlarged 120%
across.
So, if you do that, then the browser
font is going to be changed, okay? It
changes the root font size.
So, you can change it change it across
the system or you can change it on the
Mac the same, okay? On the Mac.
Or you can change it via the browser, of
course.
Uh
t s uh alt t s to go to the browser
settings in Firefox and click on that.
And uh you have uh customize relate uh
related settings customize zoom and
fonts font
settings there. So, you can see right
now I changed my font size the default
font size to 22.
The default is 16.
Uh when I do YouTube, I change it to 22
because otherwise it's too small.
So, but people older people uh
especially, you know, on the phone or on
on their laptop or desktop, usually they
have larger font, you know. So, the
default is 16. So, older people might
have it 18.
You know, so via system or via browser
settings.
So, when when when that happens, the REM
value also changes accordingly, but the
pixel value does not.
So,
let's say if you are designing uh you
know, the
the responsive design. So, this media
query CSS.
Now, if you don't know web web dev, then
you don't know what I'm talking about.
But for those of you who know web dev,
okay, web design. Cascading style sheet,
you can check out, you know, check out
my um
my fantastic visual CSS tutorial, okay?
So, I've been working on this a lot in
the past uh
in in this year in the past 3 4 months.
So, anyway, let's go back to the blog.
So, let's go back to the media query.
So, we were talking about why you should
not use pixel. So, when
people have changed their font size,
then but the pixel value doesn't change.
So, So, you thought, you know, this
should be the size and you want to do
something, right? So, media query width
is this much, then you want to do
something something.
But when people change their
uh font size,
this
width you wanted actually also changed
because the font uh
yeah, the viewport is shrink kind of. If
If people increase their font size, the
viewport actually shrink on the phone
and as well as on Windows.
So, you So, your width
is no longer what you expected, okay?
Because the pixel value does not change.
It It It's in fact um it's larger
than you expected.
Uh wait, is it larger or smaller?
Anyway, this is always confusing. So,
anyway, the point is that the pixel size
never changes, but the root font size
REM unit change according to people's
change of font.
So,
meaning that if you use pixels, you you
will have unexpected result.
Okay, for example, on a phone, on a
small phone, typically you have 300
or 320 pixels width,
okay, on a small phone.
Uh but if you enlarge the font on the
phone, then you have less than that.
You have like
280 or 300. I know because I I you know,
I enlarged the size.
So, but So, if you use pixels, you you
know, you are checking the wrong value.
So, that is why it's recommended if you
do media query, you should use the REM
value or EM.
EM
uh you can also use EM
uh
because EM means the same as REM in the
media under the media query, okay? So,
anyway, that's the reason
that is the reason you want So, this is
one thing.
If you are designing website, you media
query responsive design,
you better use REM. Don't use pixels,
okay?
I mean, even though pixels is easier to
work with, okay? So,
So, you know, because you got rulers
that show pixels. So, anyway, once you
got a pixel, you know what pixel you
want. Divide that Divide that by 16,
then you get your REM value you can use,
okay?
So, this is about media query.
So, I started to rework my cascading
style sheet, you know? So, I I got a
bunch of pixels before.
Uh I got a bunch of for media query got
I got a bunch of pixel before. So, let's
try the command again. Press press, you
see 672 pixels. Press press, becomes 42
REM. Fantastic.
So, anyway, I started to convert my uh
CSS, and it's very tedious, you know?
For example, if you don't have this easy
command, then you
you um
ca- calculator, you take out your
calculator, then, you know, let's say
you have 700 pixels divided by 16, then
it's 43.175
REM, then you go back to the CSS,
you insert that, you know, tedious.
So, now I just press a key, and you can
toggle. So, that is that command, okay?
Uh anyone here say hi, okay? So, that is
that command, and that is why we are
using we are doing it. I wrote it on the
spot. That's the power of Emacs Lisp.
That's the power of knowing Emacs Lisp.
Okay, so, now what we do? So, we
demonstrated some of these things, okay?
JavaScript block, close it. Let's go
back to Emacs. Uh
blog, okay? So, what we're going to do
is I'm going to create a page
for this code, so you guys can grab it.
Okay, it's already here. It's already on
my blog, but actually I updated Yeah,
this code is the initial version. Uh
Yeah, it's initial version. I improved
it a lot.
So, let's create a new page, okay? So,
what you do is I What I do is go here,
then go to the Xah Emacs command. So,
here on this page you have about 30 or
fantastic command you can grab. For
example, copy rectangle region to kill
ring.
Uh let's pick something more useful.
Copy current line, that one for example.
So, you don't have to do selection if
you just want to copy the current line,
so
Cut current line if no selection. Copy
current line if no selection. This
should be default in Emacs. I'm not sure
why it's not. Is it default by now? I
don't I don't I don't think so, right?
Anyway, it's
I'm not sure. Anyway, I don't think so.
So,
So, anyway, what I'm saying is this Xah
Emacs command on xahlee.info you can
find about 40 50 uh
very useful commands, okay? All the
codes are there. So, we're going to add
a new one. So, let's copy that.
So, go to Yeah, so new
block of code, paste the link, linkify,
make a list, and go to the page, and
show in browser,
and let's see. Let's see.
Can you guys see me? Yes, okay.
Let's magnify one more, okay? Show in
browser. Now, where do you want the new
command to be? The toggle. Uh that's
kind of in the CSS.
You know, actually that's actually
relatively not
not used. Okay, so in this CSS section,
you see I got a command insert random
color.
So, for example
for example, let's open my CSS, go to
the top. Let's say insert random color.
What's a key? I forgot. Is it tab or
There it is. Tab or
Fantastic, you see. Okay. Close.
So, you can
copy and grab the code. Okay, so what
we're going to do? Yeah, so let's say so
search for CSS. Okay, format CSS code.
Yeah, around here we're going to need a
new one. So, let's just do um
Yeah. Okay, so paste it. So, what what
is the command about? The command is
about this toggle um
Okay, let's go back. Go back. Go back.
Uh the command name is about CSS toggle.
Okay, so
toggle
pixel or EM.
Uh yeah, so you want to name it
EMACS CSS. Okay, now change all the
hyphen to underscore. Press press.
That's good.
Uh
Okay, that's about good. Cut. Now, put
this this this will be the file name.
And go here, paste it.
Insert color, then
then remove the underscore.
Okay.
Uh toggle, let's just say pixel. Okay,
let's change this to PX. Okay.
EMACS CSS toggle PX or EM. okay. Then
here's the title CSS
um okay did I did I did I CSS
CSS
um
should I have a period or not?
Hello guys, nobody's here.
CSS toggle pixel uh em, okay. Okay,
that's good.
So now you go here, open that file, show
in browser. That's that.
Random color command Oh, this is another
command. Command convert color RGB to
HSL. That's another very useful command,
okay, for if you are working in CSS.
Okay, anyway, so
copy it, close it. Now go here.
Uh okay, yeah, open it, paste it, close
it, go here,
select this part, copy it,
back to the file, open it, then go to
the we want to change the title, okay.
Select that, paste it.
Yeah.
Uh yeah, then
do that. I call this command will change
the title over here as well. So do it,
you see.
And delete the existing content, okay.
So section uh convert RGB color, we
don't need anymore.
Now show in browser.
Okay. Now you got this topic box. These
are all related to color. Is the thing
we are doing today related to color? No.
So we don't want this topic box.
Delete. Show in browser. Empty. Now
let's change the date.
Okay.
Press press press press, you can see the
command in the pink window. That's such
HTML update article timestamp.
Okay. And we don't want the old
timestamp because this is a new page. So
show in browser. Fantastic and
beautiful. You are beautiful.
Okay.
Okay, now the page is there. Now go back
to my Emacs blog showing browser. So you
can see we have the code here. Actually,
this is old code. We have a new code
today. So let's use a new code.
Uh
so the old code, so let's see search for
pre. That's the old code here in this
section.
Uh you can pop it out, you know, so well
put it back, delete it. We don't need
it, okay? And go back to this file, copy
the file path,
go back here,
paste the
file path, linkify it,
make it the list showing browser.
So now we have a link to the proper
file.
Okay. Click, it's empty. Okay. Now you
go to Okay, so now you um now you Okay,
so let's Okay, so let me just do some um
Hm, okay.
Yeah, so Okay, so so open the file. It's
empty. Now let's grab the code. So the
code is Where is it here? Okay, so the
code is sass css mode among my other,
you know, lots of my
Emacs packages, okay? Close.
So here and today's date is August 4th
because
you know, uh it is. So copy copy that.
Okay, wait.
So normally I can What I can do is that
I can copy that and go to today's
um
Close that. Go to today's uh uh
page.
CSS toggle. Yeah, that page. Then
start a new pre-code block
block. CSS is a language. Pay Wait, not
CSS. Undo. Okay, let's start a new one.
Let's
uh Emacs Lisp.
Okay, paste.
Show in browser. So, it will
automatically syntax color the code.
You know, why call the command show in
browser, you can kind of see here.
You see ex-html open in browser.
There is a hook. So, whenever that
command is called, it will also call
another command to [snorts]
automatically syntax color all the
pre-code.
>> [snorts]
>> So, you see, this is a pre-code.
Uh
So, that's why you see syntax color. So,
I can un-syntax color, you see. Or I can
pop it out. See, now this Emacs Lisp
mode. Now, close it.
Put it back.
Now, if I show in browser, it will
syntax color this region. Show in
browser. You see.
Go back here. You see. So, all these
are, you know, just my own command. Like
Like you can see, side share HTML pop
out um
pop out source code syntax color tag
toggle syntax color tag and, you know,
like all all my commands. Okay, that's
in side HTML mode. Okay, so we we we've
done that and let's delete that CSS we
don't need.
Okay, so
that there it is a code. Okay, is it
good? Is it
uh yeah, that's good. Okay. Now, go
back.
Close it. Okay, now showing browser this
part. Let's make sure it's correct.
Uh
let's see. Go to the CSS section there.
So, that is today's code. Now, let's
make sure
it's using the
uh uh
the correct title because sometimes I
you know, anyway, so
title is correct. CSS toggle px or em.
Is it good? Yeah, go back. Okay, and
this page is good. Okay, so I think so
let's remove that empty line. So, that's
good. Okay.
Now, uh showing browser today's
statement is no date there. Okay, good.
Close. Close. Now, this CSS mode close.
Now, showing browser. Now, here is my
Emacs blog. Now, what do I have What do
I do here? See, this screenshot is from
yesterday, the initial version. Like um
you know, I need to do it, so I just
wrote it on a spot. Fantastic. And I
posted on Twitter and uh
it seems to have gotten a lot views. You
know, you know, people like that. People
like
uh
spontaneous uh things, you know.
So, I posted So, that's today's talk
show. I'm talking there.
Uh
yeah, so but can I show the Emacs thing?
Yeah.
Uh Twitter, always interesting things on
Twitter. Okay. So, but anyway, the post
I was posting about Emacs was Go back.
Go back there. Okay.
So, now 750 views. Eight 800 views,
okay?
Uh 11 likes. Oh, actually not that many.
But, anyway. So,
that's power of Emacs Lisp because
whenever you need something, you can
just create it and do it.
I think that's it for today, okay? So,
what do
What am I going to do with this?
Again, I can just leave this screenshot
here. Emacs Lisp power Insta
pixel to REM or vice versa. Fantastic,
okay? Then, there's a permalink.
Fantastic. And there's a link to my
uh
CSS tutorial media query cascading style
sheet. I mean, the responsive design.
Now, there's another news interesting
that is
finally, the CSS started to support this
less than sign, greater than sign for
media query. Fantastic.
So, before that, you have to use So, you
know, this So, here's my update. Before
that, you have to use max-width
something. min-width something in media
query. That has That's been very
confusing to me because every time I see
that, I have to think like
I have to think for 20 seconds about
like what what does it mean max, you
know? Usually, I think For example, when
I see max-width 600, I I think of it
Okay, it's usually it's a reverse. So,
max means like
means like you know, it has a maximum of
600. So, meaning that it must be
something less than 600.
>> [laughter]
>> Very confusing.
You know, the reason it's confusing
because this max-width
this syntax that usually is used as a
um
specification.
You know, it means like typically in
other places, it means I want the
maximum width to be this, okay? But when
you use that in media query, it's like
it's like a assertion, okay? It's like
okay, the maximum width
it doesn't even work.
You see?
It doesn't You see, there's a logical
inconsistency.
You know, what you really want is to
mean is the width is less than 600
pixel. That's what you really meant.
But when you say max width 600, that
doesn't make sense.
Because you see, this user screen size
What does it mean like what does it mean
the user screen size max width?
So what what if the you know, max width
600 pixel? What if the user screen size
is 800?
So it's not max width 600. You see, it's
a you know, this is supposed to return
true or false.
Any anyway, it's so it's very confusing.
So starting about 2 years ago
2024,
finally CSS all the browser
supports this
new syntax with uh
less than or greater than sign, okay?
I think that's it for today like
that's it. How many people are watching?
Seven people.
Okay.
Anything else? Um
So we talk about Okay, we How long have
I been going? So let's see, 26 minutes.
Okay, four more four more minutes, okay?
So we
we we coded Emacs list. So let's see,
okay, so we we did this um
fantastic Emac this command. We
demonstrated that and we talked about
media query.
Uh
so we talked about how you should use
REM size and this new syntax with less
than
or greater than sign. Fantastic.
Responsive design, yes, that's
fantastic. Now let's go to my visual
my CSS tutorial. Let's see
what what's some news.
Okay, there's a custom tag, very
interesting, but I'm not going to talk
about it. There's a custom attribute,
also very interesting.
Uh custom tag is actually fantastic
because you can avoid the nested dive
like every, you know, beginning and dive
dive dive, you know.
But if you have custom element that
can differentiate, you know,
differentiate,
uh have proper naming.
So custom
element tag, fantastic. Custom data
uh attribute, also fantastic.
So you can So these are correct, you
know, you you can add information there
into a tag, any tag.
Then uh I
updated my length units, lots of update.
I spent several hours.
Uh basically the whole day, you know,
half of the day today to update the
length units. Uh so what's new? Well,
>> [sighs and gasps]
>> I made the page better, okay? So
yeah, kind of rewrite. And there there
are actually a few new units I don't
have here.
So I'm going to work on it.
CSS has become extremely complex, okay?
Then CSS variable page I also updated a
lot, you know, rewrite CSS custom
property.
Okay? Then
anyway, I think that's it. Okay.
Bye, guys.
Let's see what is this
engage with your audience. What is this
plus?
Engage with your audience. Go start a
community. Go. God.
Answer viewer questions live. Start a
QA. Let's see what that does.
Say something. Start a QA. So, let's
start.
Question. Select the question. Hover
your mouse over
any question, then click the that menu.
Pin the question for everyone to see.
Oh.
So, is this AI based? What What the heck
is this? End QA. Go to channel.
>> [laughter]
>> So, is this Is this Is this actually AI
based? Question.
Fan funding. Okay.
Anyway, that's it. That's it for today.
Let's go back.
Yeah.
Bye, guys.